in 2001,
في 2001
I returned to my old elementary school
عدت إلى مدرستي الاعدادية
to talk to the students about being an author
لأتكلم مع الطلاب عن كوني مؤلفًا
and an illustrator,
ورسامًا
and when I was setting up my slide projector
وبينما كنت أركّب عارض الصور
in the cafetorium,
في الكافتيريا
I looked across the room,
نظرت عبر الغرفة
and there she was:
وكانت واقفة هناك
my old lunch lady.
طباخة المطعم الخاصة بي
She was still there at the school
كانت لا تزال هناك في المدرسة
and she was busily preparing lunches for the day.
وكانت مشغولة بإعداد الغداء لهذا اليوم
So I approached her to say hello,
لذلك اقتربت منها لأحييها
and I said, "Hi, Jeannie! How are you?"
وقلت " هاي جيني كيف حالك؟"
And she looked at me, and I could tell
فنظرت إلي وأستطيع أن أقول
that she recognized me,
أنها تعرفت علي
but she couldn't quite place me, and she looked at me and she said,
لكنها لم تستطع تحديدي ونظرت إلي وقالت
"Stephen Krosoczka?"
"ستيفين كروسوكزكا"
And I was amazed that she knew I was a Krosoczka,
وكنت مذهولًا أنها عرفت أنني من عائلة كروسزكزكا
but Stephen is my uncle who is 20 years older than I am,
لكن ستيفن هو عمي الذي يكبرني 20 سنة
and she had been his lunch lady when he was a kid.
وقد كانت طباخة المطعم عندما كان صغيرًا
And she started telling me about her grandkids,
وبدأت تحكي لي عن أحفادها
and that blew my mind.
وهذا الشيء صدمني بشدة
My lunch lady had grandkids,
طباخة المطعم الخاصة بي لديها أحفاد!!
and therefore kids,
وهذا يعني أن لديها أطفالًا!
and therefore left school at the end of the day?
وهذا يعني أنها تغادر المدرسة في نهاية الدوام؟
I thought she lived in the cafeteria
كنت أعتقد أنها تعيش في المطعم!
with the serving spoons.
مع ملاعق السفرة.
I had never thought about any of that before.
لم أفكر بأي من هذا من قبل!
Well, that chance encounter inspired my imagination,
حسنًا، هذه الصدفة قد ألهمت خيالي،
and I created the Lunch Lady graphic novel series,
وأنشأت سلسلة روايات مصورة باسم طباخة المطعم
a series of comics about a lunch lady
سلسلة قصص مصورة عن طباخة مطعم
who uses her fish stick nunchucks
والتي تستعمل أعواد السمك كسلاح النانتشاك
to fight off evil cyborg substitutes,
لمحاربة البدائل الفضائية الشريرة
a school bus monster, and mutant mathletes,
ووحش حافلة المدرسة ومحبي الرياضيات المتحولين
and the end of every book,
وفي نهاية كل كتاب
they get the bad guy with their hairnet,
يمسكون بالشخص الشرير بشبكة الشعر
and they proclaim, "Justice is served!"
ثم ينادون (العدالة تحققت!)
(Laughter) (Applause)
(تصفيق) (ضحك)
And it's been amazing, because the series
وقد كانت رائعة، لأن السلسلة
was so welcomed into the reading lives of children,
كانت مرحبًا بها من قبل الأطفال
and they sent me the most amazing letters
فقد أرسلوا لي أروع الرسائل
and cards and artwork.
والبطاقات والأعمال الفنية
And I would notice as I would visit schools,
وكنت ألاحظ بينما أزور المدارس،
the lunch staff would be involved in the programming
طاقم العمل في المطبخ من ضمن برنامج الزيارة
in a very meaningful way.
بطريقة ذات مغزى
And coast to coast,
ومن الساحل للساحل
all of the lunch ladies told me the same thing:
كل عاملات المطبخ يخبرنني بنفس الشيء
"Thank you for making a superhero in our likeness."
"شكرا لأنك صنعت بطلا خارقا علي شاكلتنا
Because the lunch lady has not been treated
لأن عاملات المطبخ لم يعاملوا
very kindly in popular culture over time.
بشكل طيب في الثقافة العامة طوال الوقت
But it meant the most to Jeannie.
لكن هذا الأمر عنى الكثير لجيني
When the books were first published,
عندما نشر الكتاب لأول مرة
I invited her to the book launch party,
دعوتها لحفل غداء للكتاب
and in front of everyone there,
وأمام كل الناس هناك
everyone she had fed over the years,
كل الذين أطعمتهم طوال هذه الأعوام
I gave her a piece of artwork and some books.
أعطيتها عملا فنيا وبعض الكتب
And two years after this photo was taken,
وبعد عامين من التقاط هذه الصورة
she passed away,
توفيت
and I attended her wake,
وقد حضرت جنازتها
and nothing could have prepared me for what I saw there,
ولم أكن جاهزًا لما رأيته هناك
because next to her casket was this painting,
لأنه بجانب قبعتها كان هناك هذه الرسمة
and her husband told me it meant so much to her
وزوجها قال لي أنها عنت لها الكثير
that I had acknowledged her hard work,
أنني أقررت بعملها الجاد
I had validated what she did.
أنني شعرت بقيمة ما فعلته
And that inspired me to create a day
وهذا ألهمني لأنشئ يوما
where we could recreate that feeling
حيث نعيد خلق هذه المشاعر
in cafeterias across the country:
في المطعم حول البلاد
School Lunch Hero Day, a day where kids
(يوم بطلة مطعم المدرسة)، يوم حيث يمكن للأطفال
can make creative projects for their lunch staff.
صنع مشروعات خلاقة لطاقم المطعم الخاص بهم
And I partnered with the School Nutrition Association,
وأنا قمت بالتشارك مع منظمة الغذاء الصحي المدرسي
and did you know that a little over 30 million kids
هل كنت تعلم أنه أكثر بقليل من 30 مليون طفل
participate in school lunch programs every day.
يشاركون ببرامج الغداء المدرسي كل يوم
That equals up to a little over five billion lunches
هذا يساوي أكثر بقليل من 5 مليار وجبة غداء
made every school year.
تصنع كل سنة دراسية.
And the stories of heroism go well beyond
وقصص البطولة ذهبت أبعد مما نتصور
just a kid getting a few extra chicken nuggets
من مجرد طفل يحصل على أصابع دجاج إضافية
on their lunch tray.
على صينية الغداء الخاص به.
There is Ms. Brenda in California,
هنالك السيد بريندا في كاليفورنيا.
who keeps a close eye on every student that comes through her line
والذي يراقب كل طالب يمر من الطابور
and then reports back to the guidance counselor
ثم يزود المستشار الموجه بالمعلومات
if anything is amiss.
ما إن كان هنالك أي نقص.
There are the lunch ladies in Kentucky
هنالك عاملات الغداء في كنتاكي
who realized that 67 percent of their students
لاحظوا أن 67 بالمئة من طلابهم
relied on those meals every day,
يعتمدون يوميًا على هذه الوجبات،
and they were going without food over the summer,
وأنهم سيكونون بلا طعام خلال عطلة الصيف،
so they retrofitted a school bus
لذا قاموا بتعديل حافلة مدرسة
to create a mobile feeding unit,
لإحداث وحدة إطعام متجولة،
and they traveled around the neighborhoods
وقاموا بالتنقل حول الأحياء
feedings 500 kids a day during the summer.
ليطعموا يوميًا 500 طفلًا خلال عطلة الصيف.
And kids made the most amazing projects.
وقد أعد الأطفال أروع المشاريع.
I knew they would.
عرفت أنهم سيفعلون.
Kids made hamburger cards
صنعوا بطاقات الهامبرغر
that were made out of construction paper.
صنعوها من الورق المقوى.
They took photos of their lunch lady's head
كما أخذوا صورًا لرؤوس عاملات الغداء
and plastered it onto my cartoon lunch lady
وألصقوها على شخصية عاملة الغداء خاصتي
and fixed that to a milk carton
ووضعوها على علبة حليب كرتونية
and presented them with flowers.
وقدموها مع الأزهار.
And they made their own comics,
كما صنعوا قصصهم المصورة الخاصة بهم،
starring the cartoon lunch lady
من بطولة شخصية طباخات الغداء الخاصة بهم
alongside their actual lunch ladies.
إلى جانب طباخة المطعم التي ابتكرتها.
And they made thank you pizzas,
كما صنعوا بيتزا (شكرًا لك)،
where every kid signed a different topping
حيث وقع كل طفل بزينة مختلفة
of a construction paper pizza.
من بيتزا الورق المقوى.
For me, I was so moved by the response
بالنسبة لي، لقد تأثرت كثيرًا بردة الفعل
that came from the lunch ladies,
التي أتت من عاملات الغداء،
because one woman said to me, she said,
لأن إحداهن قالت لي:
"Before this day, I felt like I was
"قبل هذا اليوم، كنت أشعر أنني
at the end of the planet at this school.
في آخر الكوكب في هذه المدرسة.
I didn't think that anyone noticed us down here."
لم أفكر أن أي أحد يرانا ونحن في الأسفل."
Another woman said to me,
امرأة أخرى قالت لي:
"You know, what I got out of this
"هل تعرف ما الذي حصلت عليه من كل هذا
is that what I do is important."
هو أن ما أقوم به أمر هام."
And of course what she does is important.
وطبعًا ما تقوم به أمر هام.
What they all do is important.
ما يقمون به جميعهم هام.
They're feeding our children every single day,
إنهم يطعمون أطفالنا كل يوم،
and before a child can learn,
فقبل أن يتمكن الطفل من التعلم،
their belly needs to be full,
يجب أن تكون معدته ممتلئة،
and these women and men
هؤلاء الرجال والنساء
are working on the front lines to create
يعملون في الخطوط الأولى لخلق
an educated society.
مجتمع متعلم.
So I hope that
لذا أتمنى أن
you don't wait for School Lunch Hero Day
لا ننتظر يوم (بطل غداء المدرسة)
to say thank you to your lunch staff,
لتقول شكرًا لعاملي الغداء،
and I hope that you remember
وأتمنى أن تتذكر
how powerful a thank you can be.
كم يمكن أن تكون كلمة الشكر قوية.
A thank you can change a life.
شكرًا تستطيع أن تغير حياة.
It changes the life of the person who receives it,
إنها تغير حياة الشخص الذي يتلقاها،
and it changes the life of the person
وتغير حياة الشخص
who expresses it.
الذي يعبر عنها.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)